Guide to the Bunyan S. Womble papers, 1900-1976
Duke University. University Archives
Bunyan S. Womble papers 1900-1976
Duke University. University Archives
Womble, Bunyan S., 1882-1976.
3.9 linear feet Extent: 1800 Items
Bunyan S. Womble, graduate of Trinity College in 1904 and Trinity Law School in 1906, served actively on the Board of Trustees from 1915-1963, and then as an emeritus trustee until his death in 1976. The collection includes correspondence, reports, several newspaper clippings, memoranda, charts, and other materials. The bulk of these materials date from 1959-1963 and concern the governance and administration of the University.
UA.29.02.0026
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Records of the University's Board of Trustees which have been in existence for at least fifty years are available for scholarly research with the permission of the University Archivist. Access to records which have been in existence for less than fifty years shall be granted only by special permission, in writing, from the Board of Trustees.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Provenance
The Bunyan S. Womble papers were received by the University Archives as a gift in 1976, 1983.
Biographical Note
Womble, graduate of Trinity College in 1904 and Trinity Law School in 1906, served actively on the Board of Trustees from 1915-1963, and then as an emeritus trustee until his death in 1976. He was on the Executive Committee from 1950-1963, and was Chairman of the Board from 1960-1963.
Womble's tenure covered a critical period of growth and upheaval. He witnessed the initial admittance of African American students to Duke, President Eden's resignation, the removal of Dr. Gross from the Vice-Presidential office, the interim Hart administration, and the search for a new president that led to Douglas M. Knight. He was also on hand for the dedication of the new Law School building, and was involved in the planning of a new section of the Duke Hospital.
Collection Overview
The materials within the first and second box include correspondence, reports, several newspaper clippings, memoranda, charts, and other materials. The bulk of these materials date from 1959-1963 and concern the governance and administration of the University. Among the subjects found in the papers are the building of the Law School, the Board of Trustees, the place of religion in the curriculum, the Research Triangle Institute, and the integration of the University.
The third box consists entirely of photographs. The photographs include: 8 Trinity College scenes, 31 portraits of classmates (primarily from the Trinity class of 1904), 1 portrait of John Carlisle Kilgo, 1 portrait of a baseball player (in uniform but unidentified), 1 dormitory room (circa 1904), and 30 miscellaneous and unidentified photographs. The unidentified photos appear to be mostly of family and friends, circa 1900-1910.
Minutes of the Board of Trustees and the Executive Committee have been removed and placed in the Board's records. A newspaper clipping file on the Edens-Gross controversy has also been removed and placed in Small Collections.
Subject Headings
Duke University; Duke University -- Administration; Duke University. Board of Trustees; Integration in higher education; Womble, Bunyan S., 1982-1976
Separated Material
Minutes of the Board of Trustees and the Executive Committee have been removed and placed in the Board's records. A newspaper clipping file on the Edens-Gross controversy has also been removed and placed in Small Collections.
Related Material
Biographical Reference Collection, 1972 - 2004
University Archives, Duke University.
Board of Trustees Records, 1860 - 2004
University Archives, Duke University.
J. Deryl Hart Records, 1957 - 1980
University Archives, Duke University.
News Service Biographical Files, 1960 - 2004
University Archives, Duke University.
University Archives Photograph Collection
University Archives, Duke University.
Contents of Collection
- Container List, 3 Boxes
  - Biddle, Mary Duke Estate, 1960-1962 (Box 1)
  - Board of Trustees, 1960-1964 [RESTRICTED] (Box 1)
  - Board of Trustees, Building Committee, 1960-1962 [RESTRICTED] (Box 1)
  - Board of Trustee, Bylaws Committee, 1960-1962 [RESTRICTED] (Box 1)
  - Board of Trustees, Committees, 1962-1963 [RESTRICTED] (Box 1)
  - Board of Trustees, Correspondence, 1962-1968 [RESTRICTED] (Box 1)
  - Board of Trustees, Executive Committee (1), 1960-1963 [RESTRICTED] (Box 1)
  - Board of Trustees, Executive Committee (2), 1960-1963 [RESTRICTED] (Box 1)
  - Board of Trustees, New and Prospective Members of the Board, 1960-1964 [RESTRICTED] (Box 1)
  - Board of Trustees, Plans for Medical Center Addition- Architecture of Duke, 1963 [RESTRICTED] (Box 1)
  - Board of Trustees, Presidential Selection Committee, 1962 [RESTRICTED] (Box 1)
  - Brower, Alfred Smith "Sol" (Duke University Business Manager), 1959 (Box 1)
  - Bryson, E. C. (Duke University Attorney), 1963 (Box 1)
  - Class of 1904, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Commencement, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1962 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence Regarding Chairmanship of Board of Trustees and Chester Davis Article, 1960-1972 [RESTRICTED] (Box 1)
  - Cushman, Robert (Dean of School of Religion/Divinity School) (Information on Presidential Search), 1962 (Box 1)
  - Davison, W. C., Symposium on the Commonwealth of Children, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Divinity School (Includes correspondence with Dean Robert Cushman, plans for expansion), 1960-1965 (Box 1)
  - Duke Chronicle, 1961-1963 (Box 1)
  - Duke University Alumni Affairs, National Council, 1961-1965 (Box 1)
  - Duke University Bequest Committee, 1960-1965 (Box 1)
  - Duke University Center for Southern Studies, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Duke University Development Office and Program, 1958-1965 (Box 1)
  - Duke University Development, Fifth Decade, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - Duke University Faculty Benefits, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Duke University Faculty-Trustee Liaison Committee, 1960-1963 (Box 1)
  - Duke University Founder's Day, 1960-1964 (Box 1)
  - Duke University Half-Century Club, 1959-1965 (Box 1)
  - Duke University Integration, 1960-1962 (Box 1)
  - Duke University Investments, 1961-1963 (Box 1)
  - Duke University Loyalty Fund, 1964-1972 (Box 1)
  - Duke University, Objectives of the University, 1958-1962 (Box 1)
  - Duke University Open House Policy, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - Duke University, Religion at Duke, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Duke University, Symposia at Duke, 1963-1965 (Box 1)
  - Edens, A. Hollis Speeches, 1949-1958 (Box 1)
  - Edens Resignation, Memoranda and Correspondence (1), 1957-1960 (Box 1)
  - Edens Resignation, Memoranda and Correspondence (2), 1958-1976 (Box 1)
  - Hart, Deryl (President), Correspondence, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Hart, Deryl (President), Cottage at Roaring Gap, 1954-1960 (Box 1)
  - Honorary Degree Received at Duke University, Correspondence, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Knight, Douglas M, 1962-1966 (Box 2)
  - Knight, Douglas M. Inauguration, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Lake James Parties, 1958-1970 (Box 2)
  - Latty, Elvin Remus "Jack", 1967 (Box 2)
  - Law School, 1958-1963 (Box 2)
  - Law School Development Advisory Committee, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Law School, Miscellaneous Information Used by B.S. Womble for the Dedication of the Law School Building, 1905-1963 (Box 2)
  - Legislation (Effects on Duke), 1962 (Box 2)
  - Medical School, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Perkins, Thomas L., 1961-1964 (Box 2)
  - Presidential Search (1), 1960-1965 (Box 2)
  - Presidential Search (2), 1960-1965 (Box 2)
  - Research Triangle Institute, 1960-1963 (Box 2)
  - Research Triangle Institute, Printed matter and promotional material, 1959-1961 (Box 2)
  - Reynolds, W.N. Memorial Scholarship Fund, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Sanford, Terry, 1963-1970 (Box 2)
  - Tisdale, Wright, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - Traditions (of Duke), 1952-1963 (Box 2)
  - Violence on Campus, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Womble Scholarship Fund (Law School), 1969-1972 (Box 2)
  - Photographs, c. 1900-1910 (Box 3)